Hello, welcome back to our course, and let us get started with learning R.
What is R? R is a programming environment mainly used for data manipulation,
calculation and graphical display. R can be regarded as an implementation of the S language,
and it was written by Ihaka and Gentlemen in New Zealand in the 90s.
R is great, because it's an open source software, and it offers a great variety of
packages covering all fields of statistics and machine learning. It is also available for Windows, Linux, or Mac.
We have already learned how to download and install R on
our machines, and we definitely do not recommend using the R Graphical User Interface
for the development. Instead, it would be a good idea to use a good
text editor, or an integrated development environment. In this course, we are going to use RStudio, but
feel free to use any other of your choice. And we have already seen that particular window, so you might remember that in R studio, we have
4 panes. We have a pane with an editor, we have a pane with a console,
we have a pane with these tabs for environment, workspace and the history.
And we have a pane with tabs for files, plots, packages, help, etc.
How can we use R? Well, definitely we could use it as a calculator, so we could use it for adding numbers,
we could use it for subtracting numbers, multiplying numbers, dividing, taking a power of a number,
doing integer division or modular operators. There are also many pre-programmed functions we could apply to
numbers, for example SQRT. Apply to a number gives us the square root of that particular number. So here we have a square root of 2.
Then, also, sine, cosine, and tangent are pre-programmed. So, for example, if we apply SIN
to pi, we'll get a sine of
this constant pi, which is also pre-programmed in R.
We have also R cosine, R sine, etc., exponent, and here, another example of a pre-programmed function is,
natural logarithm, which is just log applied to a particular number.
Right. There are also many other functions, for example a floor function applied to pi gives us
the largest integer, smaller equal to pi. So in this case, it would be 3.
A ceiling function applied to pi gives us the smallest integer, larger equal than pi. In this case, it would be 4.
We have also trunc function, which, after applying it to
pi, would give us an integer, but closer to zero. So basically, here, we can see that 3 is closer to 0 than 4, so definitely we'd get 3.
But now, attention when it comes to using trunc and floor to negative numbers, because here, once again, trunc, what trunc does, is to
give us an integer part closer to zero. So if we apply trunc to minus pi,
integer part closer to 0 is minus 3. Whereas, for floor function, applied to minus pi,
we have the largest integer smaller equal than minus pi. In this case it's
minus 4. So, as you can see, trunc and floor applied to negative numbers,
give us, different outputs, minus 3 minus 4. Whereas trunc and floor applied to positive
numbers give us the same output. There is also a round function,
which is basically, applied once again to number pi, and it gives us the nearest integer, in this case, it's 3.
Right. And now, let us talk about logical operators, so definitely we have a smaller, smaller or equal, larger, larger or equal,
unequal and equal, and how can we test them? Well, we could ask, is 2 smaller than 3, and then the answer is
yes, it's true. Then we have an ampersand symbol for AND,
and a vertical bar, symbol for OR. And if we use ampersand or vertical bar once,
it also applies to vectors, so basically it applies to every element of a vector, is an element-wise operator.
Whereas if we use it twice, then it only applies to the first element of a vector,
or just a scalar. And once again, here we could test if they work, we could ask R: "Is 2 smaller than 3 AND
is 2 larger than 4?" and the answer is clearly false, because the second element
is not satisfied here. Alright, how do you write R scripts?
So definitely you could write them in the editor, so it was, the
top left pane in RStudio. And then, these codes could be stored in files with ending .r.
And then to run single lines from a script, we could just hit
Ctrl and Enter, and then definitely I advise you to
comment on your code, using this hashtag. So if I write hashtag, this line is a comment, then
R knows that this is just a comment, and it shouldn't execute the operation in that particular line.
Now, let us briefly talk about objects, so what is an object? An object in R
can be nearly everything. It can be scalar, a matrix, a function, or even a plot.
And the name of an object can be every combination of letters, numbers, and special characters.
Names should begin with the letter, and Names are case sensitive.
This is, like, something to be reminded while you code. This is very important.
And, also overwriting objects causes no warning in R, something, another thing to have a note of.
Now let us talk about the variable assignment. So, if we'd like to
assign 2 to A, what do I do? I just write A
and an arrow directed at A, and then I write 2.
We could also use the equality symbol, so I could also use here B equals 2.
This arrow could be directed in the different direction, so I could assign 2 to C.
And now, always the arrow directs towards the name of a variable.
And then we could also do the assignment in one line. So basically, I could write D is E is F is 3.
And we could definitely also use the assign function. And while he printed the results, we could definitely
print them, like, by asking to have printed C, E, and Y in one line, but this is not really recommended, it's not a great coding style to have them all in one line
and with that semicolon. So, as you can see, there are many choices when it comes to variable assignment.
This arrow is recommended in Headley Wickham's style guide,
but of course select whatever works for you. When it comes to my personal usage,
I use arrows for functions and this quality sign for variables,
vectors and matrices. Now, if we would like to list
all the objects, then we just can type ls and parentheses, and we have all the objects listed, so these are all the objects you saw.
in the past slice: a, b, c, d, e, f, y.
If we would like to remove one object from a workspace, then what do we type? We type
rm(a), because I would like to remove object a, and indeed
once again, once I type ls(), a is removed. If I would like to remove all objects, then we can write
rm list equals to ls, and it removes all objects. And as you can see now, if I type ls,
there are no objects in my workspace. Now let us briefly talk about data types. So, we could use, function mode applied to object,
to get the object's type. So we have different types of objects. So, for example, we could have a character.
A character is a string of arbitrary characters. And these are always enclosed in quotation marks
like this one, or the other one. We could also have a numeric as a type, which is, for example, a real number.
And, logical, true or false, and complex number, a function or a list. And here, as you can see, once I apply
mode, for example, to that character string, to "Hallo", then I get
character as an object type, if I applied it to TRUE, then I get logical
as an object type. When it comes to the R main structures:
We have vectors. Vectors are one-dimensional arrays of, for example, length m.
And in vectors, all elements must be of the same type.
Matrices are two-dimensional, m times n arrays. In the array, all elements must be of the same time once again.
And then, an array: It's a generalization of matrices
and it can be more than two-dimensional. Very useful data frames, so data frames are two-dimensional structures
like matrices, but data frames allow different types in different columns, and this is very handy for data analysis. You'll see that you'll work a lot with
data frames, and we have lists, once again, extremely popular, because this is a collection of objects of arbitrary types and structure, so very, very handy
while doing data analysis. Now, let us talk about classes. So, the class of an object
determines how it is treated, and this is related to object-oriented programming.
And then to learn about the class of an object, we apply class
to our object, and we get its particular class. So, all object types
correspond to classes. A vector, it's not its own class. So, basically, if I apply
class to a vector, it will return the type of its element. So, for example, if I have numbers, it will return
"numeric", if I have some letters or names, it will return "character", etc.
All other main structures listed here, apart from the vector,
have their own distinct classes. And all the important classes include integer, so here we have integer values, and factor.
Factor is categorical data stored as integers with associated labels.
We have also these two, other handy functions, is.*() a certain name, and as.*() a certain name.
So, basically, if we write is.*() and a certain class, we are asking:
"Is a particular object of this certain class, so is this numeric?"
If we apply it, for example, to 1, and then we have an answer, yes, this is numeric.
If we apply is.character() to 1,
then we have false, because it's clearly not character, it's numeric.
as.*(), so as and the name of a class,
this function attempts to coerce an object to
a particular kind. So, for example, here, if I type as.character,
it will try to coerce, so change, the class of this particular object to a
character 1, and then indeed what has happened, it has done it. So now one is
treated as a character, not a number anymore. Right, so,
first of all here, what is a workspace? A workspace in R, is all the objects, vectors, scalars, functions, created in a particular session.
And you might remember that in R studio, workspace was visible
on the Environment tab.
At the top right. And, when it comes to the history: History
has all the commands typed in a session. So, once again, in RStudio, it was under history tab
on the top right, once again.
Now, a few other very handy functions. So, for example, if I would like to set a working directory, so basically where
all the output should go to, then I could just type setwd(),
and then my working directory. Then, if I would like to get a working directory, I type getwd().
If I would like to save a workspace to an R data,
then I type save.image(). And if you would like to, save a history, so all the commands,
I type safehistory(). To load a workspace, I can just write load(),
and then in the quotation marks, this R data. And if I would like to load the history, I can just type
loadhistory(). And actually, once I do it, it enables me to browse through history
in command line, using up and down. A few other handy functions, so source():
What does source do? So, if I apply source to this R file, then basically source executes everything what's there. So functions, it just,
saves variables to the environment, etc. Now, sink(). What does sink so? So, sink, first
creates a file, and here the file will be called abc.txt,
and then, it captures everything from the console output. So here, if I type
sink(abc.txt), the file is created, then I type 3 plus 5.
Then, in that particular file, I would have 8 captured. And then if I would like to close
sink, then I just need to write sink(). And two other functions, very handy ones, q() and quit(), it
allows us to quit R. Okay, and now let us
talk about R packages. Packages are very useful, because they are bundles of functions and datasets,
and before using a package, we need to install it on our machine.
How do we do it? We can call this function install.packages,
and then, in the quotation marks, we write the name of a package.
To access a package's content, we must load it and attach it to our particular session.
How do we do it? Well, we just type library(), and once again, the name of a package, or require(). And once again, the name of a package.
Here, remember that every time we start a new session and we would like to access
the package's content, we'd need to call it back, so using library or require, whereas installing packages
is done only once. Library() throws an error,
if the package is not found. Whereas, require() only gives us a warning
and returns false. If you only want to use a single function from a package, you don't need to load it, actually,
you can access that function directly. So how do we do it? We just type the name of a package
:: and then the name of a function. Now, let us look at the example. So, I would like to install package mvtnorm,
so install.packages("mvtnorm")
Then, if I would like to, update packages, then I could also type update.packages.
If I would like to remove packages from my machine. I could type remove.packages.
Now, if I would like to show all installed libraries, I type library().
And then, if I would like to load and attach library, and you are going to use it a lot while coding, then I write library("mvtnorm"),
or require("mvtnorm"). Now, if I would like to use only one function from that particular package
function here, dmvnorm, I call mvtnorm:: and then the name of a function, and then I call this particular
function. We could also use search(), to show attached packages and data frames, and ls(2) and then here the second element, what does it do? Well, it shows us
functions for the second package.
How do we get help? Well, definitely, we can just type
help(), and then this would display the help page for a topic. For example, if I would like to get some help for the sin function, then I just write
help(sin). Question mark, and you might remember I used question mark in our video with the intro to RStudio,
this is equivalent to help. If we type help.search(),
then it searches the help system for a character string, so it would
just basically show us all the functions, elements of the help system,
where this string appears. And, ?? is equivalent to help search.
help.start() opens the HTML version of R's documentation. And if we'd like to get some info about a particular package,
then we could just type library(help = "name of the package").
For example, if I would like to get some info about mvtnorm
package, I just type library(help = "mvtnorm").
Of course, to get even more help. We could just google it, or use any browser of our choice. We could look at Stack Overflow, or QuickR.
Of course, nowadays, using chat boxes is extremely popular, and definitely people use it to even write entire chunks of code,
it's very, very popular. And then we also have R mailing lists, but I would say these are less
common among new users, I would say. Alright, and then, to sum it up, I will just conclude with a list of readings. Of course
there are plenty of books and multitude of resources on R, because R is popular
among many, many communities in research and industry. And there are many books, I would definitely
recommend you to have a look at this Hadley Wickham's style guide.
But please have a look, maybe you'll find something which is particularly
amusing and interesting for you. Okay, so thank you for today, and I see you at the next video. Thank you.